{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This organization was founded partially in response to the Springfield Race Riots of 1908, and helped investigate the Elaine Race Riot of 1919. As a result of this group’s actions, racial restrictions on military officers were removed during World War One. In 1915, this group organized a protest against the pro-KKK film, Birth of a Nation. For ten points, name this organization founded by W. E. B. Du Bois [[doo-BOYS]] to promote civil rights for African-Americans.",
      "answer": [
        "NAACP",
        "the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In this city, the Albizzi family came to power as a result of the Ciompi [[CHOM-pee]] Revolt in 1378. Filippo Brunelleschi [[broo-nell-ESK-ee]] won a competition to complete the Santa Maria del Fiore [[fee-OR-ay]] Cathedral in this city in 1418. This guild republic rose to European prominence as a result of its banking prowess. Patrons of this city’s leader, Lorenzo, included Da Vinci and Michelangelo. For ten points, name this important Tuscan city ruled by the Medici family.",
      "answer": "Florence or Firenze"
    },
    {
      "question": "The basin of the Powder River separates this mountain range from the Bighorn Mountains to the west. This mountain range provides an alternate name for the Great Sioux War of 1876. The name of the tallest peak in this mountain range was changed from Harney Peak to Black Elk Peak in 2016. Gutzon Borglum designed a monument showing the faces of four presidents in this range. For ten points, what hills contain Mount Rushmore in South Dakota?",
      "answer": "Black Hills"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the Poetic Edda, these mythological figures gave the name Helgi to the unnamed son of King Hjorvardr [[HYOR-var-deer]]. An 11th century runestone features a carving of one of these mythological figures handing a drinking horn to the hero Sigurd. These mythological figures are said to oversee the einherjar [[AYN-hare-jar]] in the halls of Valhalla. With a name translating to “chooser of the slain,” for ten points, name this group of female Norse warriors.",
      "answer": "Valkyries 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 1"
    },
    {
      "question": "Arnold Constable & Company, which New York newspapers called the “Palace of Trade,” was the first American example of this type of business. Postmaster General John Wanamaker founded one of these businesses in Philadelphia, which housed the largest pipe organ in the world. One of these enterprises was developed from a mail-order catalog by A.C. Roebuck and Richard Sears. For ten points, name these retail companies that include Kohl’s and Macy’s.",
      "answer": "Department stores"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city's \"Maidens\" were transported to Mount Sinai Hospital in New York for treatment of keloid scars. The dome of the Industrial Promotion Hall in this city now serves as its namesake Peace Memorial. A Pulitzer Prize-winning book by John Hersey chronicles six survivors of an attack on this city, on which “Little Boy\" was dropped. For ten points, what Japanese city was devastated by an atomic bomb three days before a similar attack on Nagasaki?",
      "answer": "Hiroshima"
    },
    {
      "question": "Members of this general profession like Yuri Kondratyuk [[kon-DRAT-yuk]] and Vladimir Myasishchev [[my-ah-SISS-tchoff]] worked in locations called sharashkas in Soviet gulags. The so-called \"Layer Cake\" idea by a member of this profession led to the development of the RDS-37. Trofim Lysenko created fraudulent theories while working in this profession. The activist Andrei Sakharov [[SOCK-ar-off]] held, for ten points, what general profession, practitioners of which designed the Tsar Bomba?",
      "answer": "Scientist"
    },
    {
      "question": "One person of this type, named Isaac Friend, planned a failed insurrection in York County, Virginia. Thomas Grantham put down a rebellion fueled in part by people with this status. Some English prisoners of war were forced into this condition, while many immigrants voluntarily entered into it. During Bacon’s Rebellion, many of these people revolted against the colonial elite. For ten points, name these workers who entered into voluntary servitude.",
      "answer": [
        "Indentured servants",
        ","
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This instrument was played by the Black musician George Bridgetower, the dedicatee of Beethoven’s Kreutzer Sonata. Erich Wolfgang Korngold’s concerto for this instrument was first played by Jascha [[YOSH-ah]] Heifetz. A 19th-century Italian who wrote 24 caprices for this instrument was believed by some to have sold his soul to the Devil. Niccolo Paganini played one of these instruments crafted by Stradivarius. For ten points, name this highest-pitched string instrument.",
      "answer": "Violin 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 1"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a 1958 book, this man faces a \"good son\" and \"good monk\" crisis in which he is twice born and his soul transformed. In that book, this man suffers an \"identity crisis\" in which, during a choir practice at a monastery, he shouts \"I am not!\" Following a similar work about Mahatma Gandhi, psychologist Erik Erikson wrote a psychobiography of this man, who challenged the Catholic Church at the Diet [[DEE-et]] of Worms [[VURMS]]. For ten points, name this Reformation leader who wrote the 95 Theses in Wittenberg, Germany.",
      "answer": "Martin Luther 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 1"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Bicentennial of this colony was celebrated in the Grand National Jubilee. Nikole Hannah-Jones places the consequences of slavery at the center of US history, beginning with this colony, in The 1619 Project. Tobacco seeds were brought to this colony by John Rolfe in the Third Supply, and this colony earlier had faced the \"Starving Time.\" Located a few miles southwest of Williamsburg, for ten points, name this first permanent English settlement in America.",
        "answer": "Jamestown, Virginia"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Jamestown was deliberately burned during this 1675-76 rebellion of Virginia settlers, the first in the North American British colonies.",
        "answer": "Bacon's Rebellion"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Major Hubert-Joseph Henry made a dramatic testimony during this event in which the Panizzardi telegram was investigated. Armand du Paty de Clam was promoted in this event, which was resolved when Henri Brisson resigned. Émile Zola wrote J'Accuse during this event, increasing public pressure to reopen it. The real traitor in this event was Ferdinand Esterhazy. For ten points, name this French scandal in which a Jewish officer was wrongly convicted.",
        "answer": "Dreyfus Affair"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "One of the \"Dreyfusards\" who supported Major Dreyfus during his re-trial was this Minister of the Interior and later Prime Minister of France, nicknamed \"The Tiger.\"",
        "answer": "Georges Clemenceau"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One self-critique of this work by its composer called it “very loud and noisy and completely without artistic merit.” This piece was conducted by that composer at the opening of Carnegie Hall in 1891. This work debuted at the Cathedral of Christ the Saviour, which was later demolished on the orders of Josef Stalin. For ten points, name this Pyotr Tchaikovsky concert piece that features chimes and cannons and is often played as an accompaniment to fireworks displays.",
        "answer": "The Year 1812 Solemn Overture, Op. 49"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What work, Tchaikovsky’s second and longest ballet, featuring King Florestan and his daughter, Aurora, was critiqued as “very nice” by Tsar Alexander III after its 1890 debut?",
        "answer": "The Sleeping Beauty or Spyashchaya krasavitsa 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 1"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country was once led by \"The Madman Who Loves,” Abdalá Bucaram. With a neighbor, this country's president of Lebanese descent, Jamil Mahuad, signed the Brasilia Presidential Act. After a 1972 coup, this country implemented a \"Return to the Constitution Plan.” One party in this country was named \"Alfaro Lives, Dammit!” In 2017, this country's president, Lenín Moreno, succeeded Rafael Correa. For ten points, name this South American nation, the first to call for independence in 1809.",
        "answer": "Republic of Ecuador"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "These islands are part of Ecuador and the location of Charles Darwin's studies of animals on an 1835 expedition that led to the theory of evolution.",
        "answer": [
          "Galápagos Islands",
          "Archipelago de Colón"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Using a magical hook made of ancestor bones, a trickster figure of these people raised an archipelago. One of this culture’s legends takes place at the lagoon, Mata o le Alelo, and tells the story of Sina, who fell in love with an eel who once held the title, Tui Viti. Paul Gauguin painted an interpretation of this culture’s ghosts staring at a nude girl in his Spirit of the Dead Watching. For ten points, name this people group of the Pacific whose divine figures include Maui and Pele.",
        "answer": [
          "Polynesian",
          "more specific people like Hawaiians, Tahitians,",
          "Samoans"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Kohara is the Polynesian goddess and original ancestor of this fish from the mackerel family, important to the seafaring people, some species of which are endangered due to overfishing.",
        "answer": [
          "Tuna",
          "Tunny"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "With Guntram, a leader of these people signed the Pact of Andelot. One noble of these people tried to kill Rigunth by slamming a chest shut, and that woman, Fredegund, also ordered Sigebert I's assassination. A queen of these people, Brunhilda, was executed by being pulled apart by horses. Gregory of Tours documented these people's Merovingian Dynasty. Pepin the Short and Clovis were rulers of, for ten points, what Germanic people who gave their name to France?",
        "answer": [
          "Franks",
          "Merovingians Dynasty before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Merovingian kingdom extended as far east as what is today this largely Catholic German state, an independent kingdom from 1806 to 1871, whose largest city is Munich.",
        "answer": "Free State of Bavaria 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 1"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Zero-tolerance on this border was implemented in Operation Streamline. This border was changed in the Chamizal Dispute due to river shifts. The Big Bend National Park lies on this border, and the International Boundary and Water Commission deals with water rights on this border. This border was first fixed in the Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo, and, more recently, Donald Trump proposed enhancing a wall on this border. For ten points, name this border that includes a portion of the Rio Grande.",
        "answer": [
          "United States-Mexico border",
          "US",
          "USA for United States",
          "United Mexican States",
          "EUM for Mexico"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "While Donald Trump claimed during his 2016 presidential campaign that Mexico would pay for his planned border wall, this president of Mexico, in office from 2012 to 2018, denied that his country would pay for the construction of such a wall.",
        "answer": "Enrique Peña Nieto"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A biography by Richard Norton Smith takes its title from this former president’s “Uncommon Man” speech, delivered at Wilmington College in 1948. This man was appointed by Calvin Coolidge to oversee relief efforts after the Great Mississippi Flood of 1927. During a severe economic downturn, shantytowns named for this president popped up across the nation. For ten points, name this 31st US president who served a single term during the Great Depression.",
        "answer": "Herbert Hoover"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1920, Hoover was appointed Secretary of this department which separated from the Department of Labor in 1913.",
        "answer": "US Department of Commerce"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Vice Presidential Fails",
      "prompt": "Name the Vice President who…...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Shot and killed Alexander Hamilton in an 1804 duel.",
          "answer": "Aaron Burr"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was not involved in the Watergate scandal but resigned in 1973.",
          "answer": "Spiro Agnew"
        },
        {
          "question": "Feuded with Andrew Jackson about tariffs before resigning.",
          "answer": "John C. Calhoun"
        },
        {
          "question": "Gave the “Checkers” speech following a campaign fund controversy.",
          "answer": "Richard Nixon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was implicated in the Whiskey Ring under Ulysses Grant.",
          "answer": "Schuyler Colfax"
        },
        {
          "question": "Infamously misspelled the word “potato”",
          "answer": "Dan Quayle"
        },
        {
          "question": "Arrived too late to make the tie-breaking vote for Coolidge's nominee for Attorney General.",
          "answer": "Charles G. Dawes"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was replaced on the incumbent ticket by Harry Truman due to his incompetence.",
          "answer": "Henry Wallace"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Candle Making",
      "prompt": "Name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "English capital where the Tallow Chandlers Company was located.",
          "answer": "London, England, United Kingdom"
        },
        {
          "question": "Man who is celebrated on Candlemas as well as December 25th, his birthday.",
          "answer": "Jesus Christ"
        },
        {
          "question": "Natural material used for candles that comes from honey making insects.",
          "answer": "Beeswax"
        },
        {
          "question": "Aquatic mammal hunted to near extinction for the candle-making material harvested from its head cavity.",
          "answer": "Sperm whale"
        },
        {
          "question": "Type of wax made from the material that James Young distilled from coal and oil shales.",
          "answer": "Paraffin Wax"
        },
        {
          "question": "1840 London event involving a woman wearing a William Dyce-designed dress, during which loyal households burned candles.",
          "answer": [
            "Wedding of Queen Victoria and Prince Albert",
            "Marriage in place of \"Wedding\""
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Upstate New York city named for a Sicilian city known for candle manufacturing.",
          "answer": "Syracuse"
        },
        {
          "question": "Largest candle-maker in the UK who pioneered steam distillation in manufacturing.",
          "answer": "Price's Patent Candles 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 1"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "New Kingdom Egypt",
      "prompt": "Name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Egyptian river where the Sea People were repelled after the Battle of the Delta.",
          "answer": "Nile"
        },
        {
          "question": "First name of the pharaoh who expelled the Sea People and shares his name with an earlier “Great” pharaoh.",
          "answer": "Ramesses III"
        },
        {
          "question": "First capital of the New Kingdom which shares its name with a Greek city-state.",
          "answer": "Thebes"
        },
        {
          "question": "Queen depicted on a famous bust displayed in Berlin since 1912.",
          "answer": "Nefertiti"
        },
        {
          "question": "Semitic people expelled by the New Kingdom and associated with the Israelites by Josephus.",
          "answer": "Hyksos"
        },
        {
          "question": "Pharaoh who introduced the monotheistic cult of Atenism.",
          "answer": [
            "Akhenaten",
            "Amenhotep IV"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Temple complex built by Amenhotep III and dedicated to the mother goddess Mut.",
          "answer": "Luxor Temple"
        },
        {
          "question": "Region known as “The Land of the Gods,” to which Hatshepsut sponsored many voyages in search of gold and ivory.",
          "answer": "Land of Punt 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 1"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this year, Jim Sasser and Harris Wofford lost their seats in the Senate. A document released in this year proposed the Citizen Legislature Act, which would have introduced congressional term limits. In this year, Alabama senator Richard (20 pts)",
        "Shelby switched parties and became a Republican. The Heritage Foundation worked with Larry Hunter, Tom DeLay, and Newt Gingrich in this year to write the (10 pts)",
        "Contract with America. For ten points, name this midterm election year during Bill Clinton's first term."
      ],
      "answer": "1994"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "This man lost at the Battle of Grand Turk in the Turks and Caicos. C. K. Shorter claims that the Bronte family of literary fame changed their surname to associate themselves with this man, the Duke of Bronté. With Lord Jervis, this man attacked (*) Cádiz and led an amphibious attack on Santa Cruz de Tenerife. On the Victory, this man engaged the Bucentaure and signaled, \"England expects (*) that every man will do his duty.” For ten points, name this British admiral who was killed at Trafalgar."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Horatio Nelson",
        "1st Viscount Nelson,",
        "1st Duke of Bronté before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1034, this river flooded following heavy rainfall at Henglong. This river carries sediment from the Loess plateau and has a large bend in the Ordos Loop. Historically, this river once went through Dalu Lake and Daye Lake but shifted due to floods, one of which ended the (20 pts)",
        "Xin [[SHIN]] Dynasty of Wang Mang. 890,000 people died when this river flooded after the KMT destroyed levees to stop the (10 pts)",
        "Japanese invasion. For ten points, name this second-longest Chinese river known for its muddy color."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Yellow River",
        "Huang He ]"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A leader of this country claimed that its own citizens would “eat grass,” if necessary, to develop its own nuclear arsenal if a rival nation did so. Baitullah Mehsud was accused of ordering the 2007 assassination of this country’s former prime minister, (20 pts)",
        "Benazir Bhutto. In 1940, Muhammad Ali Jinnah worked to pass the Lahore Resolution, demanding that the UK grant independence to this nation, separate from its (10 pts)",
        "majority-Hindu neighbor. For ten points, name this primarily Muslim country created by the Partition of India."
      ],
      "answer": "Islamic Republic of Pakistan 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 1"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Aaron Schock, a congressman from this state, resigned after being accused of buying luxury items with government money. Mike Madigan, Speaker of the House in this state, faced a 2020 investigation over a bribery scandal and was urged to step down by Governor J. B. (20 pts)",
        "Pritzker. An FBI operation called Silver Shovel discovered that aldermen in this state’s (10 pts)",
        "Cook County were complicit in illegal activities. For ten points, name this state where George Ryan and Rod Blagojevich [[blah-GOY-eh-vitch]] once governed from Springfield."
      ],
      "answer": "Illinois"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Pope Clement II may have been murdered using tainted sugar that caused this condition. Caravaggio's violent behavior might indicate he also died of this condition. The Washington Post claimed correlation between this condition and the decrease in crime, due to a (20 pts)",
        "substance being removed from paint and gasoline. A hypothesis concerning the collapse of the Roman Empire blames this condition occurring due to (10 pts)",
        "pipes. For ten points, name this type of metal poisoning."
      ],
      "answer": "Lead poisoning"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "A temple for this deity built during the reign of Augustus was one of the first discoveries in Pompeii. Helena Blavatsky wrote about this deity Unveiled as part of the Theosophists. The use of model boats in medieval Carnival festivals was argued to have been derived from the cult of this deity. This (*) goddess was invoked in the Ephesian Tale to protect virginity and revived her husband after he was torn into 14 pieces by (*) Set. For ten points, name this Egyptian goddess, the wife of Osiris."
      ],
      "answer": "Isis"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "This man sent \"sincere congratulations\" that an attack of \"armed hordes\" had been stopped \"without appealing to friendly powers for help.” In 1895, this man was compelled to send a cruiser to Delagoa Bay, and a telegram from him to Johannes (*) Kruger was possibly written by Adolf Marschall von Bieberstein. In the Daily Telegraph Affair, this man called the English \"mad as March hares.” Before World War One, this man sent (*) Nicholas II the Willy-Nicky letters. For ten points, name this German Kaiser."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Wilhelm II",
        "William II 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 1"
      ]
    }
  ]
}